<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The iust reckenyng or accompt of the whole nomber of the yeares, from the beginnyng of the world vnto this present yere of. 1547 A certaine and sure declaracion that the world is at an ende. Of the last day of iudgement, or day of dome, and howe it shal come to passe. Translated out of the Germaine tonge into Englishe by Anthony Scoloker the .6. daye of July. Anno D[omi]ni. 1547.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106781</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842491</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842491</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7150</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10519)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7150)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 448:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The iust reckenyng or accompt of the whole nomber of the yeares, from the beginnyng of the world vnto this present yere of. 1547 A certaine and sure declaracion that the world is at an ende. Of the last day of iudgement, or day of dome, and howe it shal come to passe. Translated out of the Germaine tonge into Englishe by Anthony Scoloker the .6. daye of July. Anno D[omi]ni. 1547.</title>
                  <author>Scoloker, Anthony, fl. 1548.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1547]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Printing sometimes attributed to Anthony Skoloker; cf. Freeman, Janet Ing, "Anthony Skoloker, the 'Just Reckoning printer' and the earliest Ipswich printing", Transactions of the Cambridge Bibliographical Society, v.IX, part 5.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks all after leaf A7.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judgement Day --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7150:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7150:1"/>
            <p>The iuſt recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng or accompt of the whole nomber of the yeares, from the beginnyng of the world vnto this preſente yere of .1547.</p>
            <p>A certaine and ſure declaracion that the world is at an ende.</p>
            <p>Of the laſt day of iudgement, or day of dome, and howe it ſhal come to paſſe.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Germaine tonge into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe by Anthony Scoloker the .6. daye of Iuly. Anno Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i. 1547.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matthew. 25.</bibl>
               <p>Watche therfore for ye knewe neither the daye nor yet the howre when the ſonne of man ☞ ſhall come. ☜</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>inverted triangle composed of decorative elements</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7150:2"/>
            <head>¶To the Reader.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as many wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters haue diuerſly wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the accompt of the time. Here haſte thou (gentle reader) the iuſte nomber of the yeares from the beginnyng of the world vnto this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t yere of .1547. dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly gathered out of the Bible.</p>
            <p>Here haſt thou alſo a certaine and ſure declaracion that the daie of dome is at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: not tha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we wil or can declare the very houre,<note place="margin">Act. 1.</note> as Chriſt ſayth. Actes. 1. But to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we ſhuld be ready at all times as true faithful ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes which waite for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng of their Lord for he ſhall not tary but com<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very ſhortly.<note place="margin">Luke. 12.</note> Therfore let vs watche and pray for we know neither houre nor time.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7150:2"/>
            <div type="list_of_eras_reckoned_since_Creation">
               <list>
                  <head>The no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the yeares brefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comprehended.</head>
                  <item>
                     <label>The .1. accompt.</label>
FRom the begynnynge of the world vnto the floud, are .1656. yeares.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>The .2. accompt.</label>
Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the floud vnto the tyme that Abraham departed out of Chaldea, are .363. yeares, and 10. daies.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>The .3. Accompt.</label>
From Abrahams departing out of Chaldea til the Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t out of Egipt, are 400. and .30. yeares.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>The .4. Accompt.</label>
From the departyng of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael out of Egipt, till the firſt buildyng of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or tyll the .4. yere of the reigne of Salomon, are .4700. yeares.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7150:3"/>
                     <label>The 5. accompt.</label>
From the firſt buyldynge of the Temple tyl the captyuitie of Babylon, are 419. yeres and 6. monethes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>The 6. accompt.</label>
From the captyuitie af Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, tyl that Ieruſalem was buylte agayne, are 143. yeres.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>The 7. accompt.</label>
From the tyme that Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem was buylt agayne, tyl the Byrthe of our ſauiour Chriſt, are 483. yeres.</item>
               </list>
               <p>From the byrth of Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this preſent yere are, 1547. Thus doth the wholl ſumme of the yeres fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the world, vnto this preſent yere of 47. amount to 5521. and ſomwhat more than halfe a yere.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="reckoning">
               <pb facs="tcp:7150:3"/>
               <p>The declaracion of the before named nomber,<note place="margin">The firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt.</note> ſet forth at large, from the begynnynge of the world, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floud, are 1656. yeres, which are nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred after this maner foloi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge.<note place="margin">Geneſ. 5.</note>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>Adam, beyng of the age of 130. begatte Seth.</item>
                  <item>Seth, beyng old 105,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 5.</note> yeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatte Enos.</item>
                  <item>Enos, beinge olde 90.<note place="margin">Geneſ. 5.</note> yere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatte Cainan.<note place="margin">Geneſ. 5.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Cainan, being olde 60 yere, begatte Malalehel.</item>
                  <item>Malalehel, bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g olde 65.<note place="margin">Geneſ. 5.</note> yeres begatte Iared.</item>
                  <item>Iared, beyng olde 162.<note place="margin">Geneſ. 5.</note> begatte Enoch.</item>
                  <item>Enoch, beyng olde 65,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 5.</note> yere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatte Mathuſalem.</item>
                  <item>Mathuſalem, beynge olde 97,<note place="margin">Geneſis. 5.</note> yere begatte Lamech.</item>
                  <item>Lamech, beyng olde 182,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 5.</note> yere begatte Noe.</item>
                  <item>Noe was of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age of 600,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 7.</note> yeres
<pb facs="tcp:7150:4"/>
whan the floud was vpon the earthe.</item>
               </list>
               <p>This mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth al in one ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me 1656 yeares.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reckoning">
               <p>From the floud till the tyme that Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> went out of Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea, are .363. yeares and .10. dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es whiche are nombred thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſis. 8.</note>The floud continued a yere and, 10. daies.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. 11.</note>Sem the ſonne of Noe begatt Arphaxat 2. yere after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floud.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. 11.</note>Arphaxat beyng olde .35. yere begatte Sale.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. 11.</note>Sale, beyng old .30. yere begat Heber.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. 11.</note>Heber, beyng olde .34. yere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatte Phalech.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. 11.</note>Phalech, beynge olde .30. yere begatte Reu.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. 11.</note>Reu, beyng olde .37. yere begat Saruch.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. 11.</note>Saruch, being old .30. yere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatte
<pb facs="tcp:7150:4"/>
Nachor.</item>
                  <item>Nachor, beyng olde 29. yere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatte Thare.<note place="margin">Geneſ. 11.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thare, beyng olde .70. yere,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 11.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatte Abraham.</item>
                  <item>Abraham, beyng olde .70.<note place="margin">Geneſ. 11.</note> yere departed out of Vr.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reckoning">
               <p>From Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s departing out of Chaldea tyll that the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell went out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipte, are .430.<note place="margin">The third ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>compt.</note> yere whiche are nombred thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was fiue yere at Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram in the .705.<note place="margin">Geneſis. 12.</note> yere departed he from thens.</item>
                  <item>In the .25.<note place="margin">Gene. 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> yere of his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge from thens (which was in the .100. yere of gis age) he begatte Iſaac.</item>
                  <item>Iſaac being olde .3.<note place="margin">Gene. 27.</note> ſcore yere begatte Iacob.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7150:5"/>
                     <note place="margin">Gene. 47.</note>Iacob was old 130, yere when he w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al his family &amp; houſhold went into Egypt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 7.</note>Hereof muſt be rebated 80, yeres, for ſo olde was Moyſes when he led the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell out of Egypt.</item>
                  <item>The ouer plus or reſt of the yeres, to ſay 130, yeres muſt be deuyded of Moyſes father &amp; grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dfather, namely Amram and Chath, ſo that Chath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge olde 67, yeres begatte Amram Moyſes father: And Amram beyng 65, yeres of age begatte Moyſes, who led the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael out of Egypt in the 80, yere of his age.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 12. Galat. 3.</note>This amounteth together to 430, as it appereth Exod 12, and Galath. 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reckoning">
               <p>From the goynge fourth out of Egypt tyl y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt byldi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The. 4. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7150:5"/>
Temple, or tyll the, 4, yere of the Reygne of Salomon are 480, yere whiche muſt be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thus,<note place="margin">Deut. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>Moſes reigned in the deſert, 40, yere,</item>
                  <item>Ioſue and Othoniel, 40, yere,<note place="margin">Iudic. 3.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Aioth, 80, yere,<note place="margin">Iudic. 8.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Delbora .40. yere.<note place="margin">Iudic. 8.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gedeon .40. yere.<note place="margin">Iudic. 9. Iudic. 10.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Abimelech .3. yere.</item>
                  <item>Thola .22. yere.<note place="margin">Iudic. 10. Iudic. 10.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>After that were they .28. yere without head, til y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pthae.</item>
                  <item>Iepthae reigned .6. yere.<note place="margin">Iudic. 12. Iudic. 12. Iudic, 12. Iudi. 12</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Abeſſam .7, yere,</item>
                  <item>Elon, 10, yere,</item>
                  <item>Abdon, 8, yere,</item>
                  <item>Sampſon, 20, yere,<note place="margin">Iudi. 16. 1. Samuel, 4</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Heli was bothe Iudge &amp; preſt 40. yere.</item>
                  <item>Samuel and Saul haue reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, 40, yere,<note place="margin">Act. 3</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7150:6"/>
                     <note place="margin">2. Regum. 5.</note>Dauid was 40. yere kynge.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">3. Reg. 6.</note>Salomon beganne to buylde the Temple in the fourth yere of his reygne.</item>
               </list>
               <p>This amounteth to gether to 470. yere, whiche are alſo ſo nombred 3. Regum. 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="reckoning">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fifth ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>compt.</note>From the firſt buyldyng of the Temple, tyl the captyuytie of Babilon, are 419. yeres and 6. monethes which muſt be rekened thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">5. Regum. 11.</note>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reigned yet 63. yeres.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">1. Paril. 12.</note>Roboam 17. yere.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">2. Paral. 13.</note>Abia 3. yere.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">3. Reg. 15. 3. Reg. 22.</note>Aſa 41. yere</item>
                  <item>Ioſaphat 25. yere.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">2. Para. 21.</note>Ioram 8. yere.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">4. Reg. 8.</note>Ochoſias 1. yere</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">4. Reg. 11. 4. Reg. 12.</note>Athalia was 7. yere Quene.</item>
                  <item>Ioas' 40 yere.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">4. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 14.</note>Amaſias 29. yere</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7150:6"/>Oſias 52. yere,<note place="margin">4. Reg. 15.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ioatham 16. yere.<note place="margin">4. Reg. 15.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Achas 16. yere.<note place="margin">4 Reg. 16. 4. Reg. 18.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ezechias 29. yere</item>
                  <item>Manaſſes 55. yere.<note place="margin">4. Reg. 21.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Amon 2. yere.<note place="margin">4. Reg. 21. 4. Reg. 22.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ioſyas 31. yere.</item>
                  <item>Ioachas 3. monethes.<note place="margin">4. Reg. 23.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ioakim Eliachim 9. yere.<note place="margin">4. Reg. 23. 4. Reg. 34.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ioachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iochonias 3. monethes</item>
                  <item>In whoſe tyme beganne the Captyuitye of Babylon in the 11. yere of zedechia wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple and cytye was burned as apereth in the 1.<note place="margin">Matt. 1.</note> chap. of Mat. and alſo in the 24, and 25.<note place="margin">Iere. 24.25.</note> chap. ter of Hieremy the prophet.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Which amounteth al in one ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e 419. yeres and 6. monethes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="reckoning">
               <p>From the captiuitye of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon til the buyldyng againe of Ieruſalem, are 143. yere.<note place="margin">The ſixte ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt.</note>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7150:7"/>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Iere. 24.25.</note>The Captiuitie continued .60, yere.<note place="margin">1, Eſdra, 1,</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>In the firſt yere of the reigne of king Cyrus were the captiues or priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ers deliuerd,</item>
                  <item>In the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yere of Cirus,<note place="margin">1, Eſdra, 2,</note> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beganne to build the Temple.</item>
                  <item>In the .46.<note place="margin">1, Eſdra, 6,</note> yere was the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plete &amp; finiſhed that is in the 6, yere of the reigne of king Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rius.<note place="margin">Nehemias, 2</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>In the, 20, yere of his rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne, was Nehemias releaſed, and came for to build the citie.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In the .22.<note place="margin">Nehem, 5,</note> yere of Darius was the citie finiſhed, ſo that the no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of yeres of the buildyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain of the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple are, 26, which amou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth togither to 143. yere.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The, 7, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt.</note>From the buildyng againe of Ieruſalem til the comming of Chriſt are .483, yere, which are nombred thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>It is written in the, 9, Chap
<pb facs="tcp:7150:7"/>
of Daniell, of the goyng for the or procedyng of the word (that is to ſaye) from the tyme that Ieruſalem ſhall be buylte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne tyll the time of the true Meſſias and Sauiour Chriſt are .67. wekes,<note place="margin">Note this wel, Lu, 25</note> and one weke is counted here for .7. yere as it appeareth, Leuiticus. 25.</item>
                  <item>Thus make, 67, wekes. 483, ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and ſo manye yeares is it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reigne of Darius, til y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 42, yere of the reigne of Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, in which yere Chriſt was borne.</item>
                  <item>Thus the noumber of the yeres from the beginnynge of the worlde tyll the byrthe of Chriſte are .3, thouſande, 974, &amp; lyttell more than halfe a yere, and from the byrthe of Chriſt tyll this preſent yere of, 47, is clere and manyfeſt inough.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7150:8"/>So that from the begynnyng of the worlde vnto this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t yere, are 5521. yere &amp; ſomewhat more then halfe a yere.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="reckoning">
               <p>Of the ende of the world, and of the daye of dome or Iudgement.</p>
               <p>I wyll not here go about to ſerche out the very hour of the Iudgement (for God <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in his powre, hath hyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the ſame) but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſtly declare that the day is euen at hand.</p>
               <p>ELyas hath ſpoken tha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the worlde ſhulde ſtand aboute 6000. yere, whic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nombre is deuyded after thi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maner 2000 yere voyde wit<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out anye lawe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7150:8"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
